

Summary

I'm a PhD student at Universitat Pompeu Fabra under the joint supervision of Gemma Boleda and Laia Mayol. My PhD research currently focuses on understanding the use of referring expressions, mainly through quantitative and computational methods.

Education

Universitat Pompeu Fabra

Barcelona, Spain

Ph.D. CANDIDATE IN LINGUISTICS

2019 - present

Universitat Pompeu Fabra

Barcelona, Spain

M.S. IN THEORETICAL AND APPLIED LINGUISTICS

2018 - 2019

• GPA: 8.68/10

· Venue: Computational Linguistics

Beijing Jiaotong University, Complutense University of Madrid

Beijing, China

B.S. IN HISPANIC PHILOLOGY

2014 - 2018

· GPA: 9.58/10 · with Honors

European Summer School in Logic, Language and Information

Virtually

2021

• Track: Language and Computation (LaCo)

Publication

Liao. (2022). Coherence-driven predictability and referential form: evidence from English corpus data. Proceedings of Sinn und Bedeutung 26, to appear.

Aina, L., Liao, X., Boleda, G., Westera, M. (2021, November). Does referent predictability affect the choice of referential form? A computational approach using masked coreference resolution. In Proceedings of the 25th Conference on Computational Natural Language Learning (pp. 454-469).

Presentation

Deep Learning Barcelona Symposium 2021

Barcelona, Spain

TALK

December 22nd, 2021

- Title: Does referent predictability affect the choice of referential form? A computational approach using masked coreference resolution
- [Recording]

UR-Ling workshop

Barcelona, Spain

November 12th, 2021

· Title: Referent predictability and referential choice

The SIGNLL Conference on Computational Natural Language Learning (CoNLL) 2021

Virtually November 11th, 2021

POSTER PRESENTATION

- Title: Does referent predictability affect the choice of referential form? A computational approach using masked coreference resolution
- [PDF], [Poster]

Sinn und Bedeutung 26

Virtually

September 9th. 2021

- Title: Coherence-driven predictability and referential form: evidence from English corpus data
- OSF

Workshop on Computational and Experimental Explanations in Semantics and **Pragmatics**

European Summer School in Logic, Language and Information (ESSLLI) 2021, Virtually

August 10th. 2021

• Title: Coherence-driven predictability and referential form: evidence from English corpus data

Student session in European Summer School in Logic, Language and Information (ESSLLI) 2021

Virtually

August 6th. 2021

2020 - 2021

· Title: Coherence-driven predictability and referential form: evidence from English corpus data

Teaching _____

Semàntica i Pragmàtica (Professor: Martina Wiltschko)

Department of Translation and Language, Univeristat Pompeu Fabra

TEACHING ASSISTANT FOR MASTER COURSES

- Compositionality and Truth(conditions)
- Modality and possible worlds; Quantifiers
- · Clausal and nominal reference
- Presuppositions
- The Gricean program. Recognizing intentions.
- · What we do when we use language: Speech act theory.
- Dynamic theories of meaning. Language in interaction.
- Expressing emotions and other non-truth-conditional meaning.

Introducció a la Universitat i Recursos (Professor: Núria Bel)

• The relation between language, thought and communication

Department of Translation and Language, Univeristat Pompeu

TEACHING ASSISTANT FOR UNDERGRADUATE COURSES

- · Build an HTML website
- · Regular expressions
- · Corpus analysis

Fahra

2020 - 2022

Professional Service

ESSLLI 2022 Student Session

CO-CHAIR

Galway, Ireland

• Track: Language and Computation (LaCo)

ORGANIZER

August 8-19, 2022

REtreat for Students in Computational Linguistics (REST-CL)

Barcelona, Spain

· Rural house

April 11-14, 2022

Work Experience _____

China's Commerce Ministry, Beijing Jiaotong University Training Center

Beijing, China

CHINESE-SPANISH INTERPRETER & TRANSLATOR IN SEMINARS FOR FOREIGN DELEGATIONS

2017 - 2018

- Bilateral Seminar of Infrastructure Between China and Uruguay.
- Seminar on Ocean Railway Construction for Perú-Brasil

Cielo Education

Beijing, China

CHINESE TEACHER FOR FOREIGNERS · Teaching elementary Chinese. 2017 - 2018

Fellowships

2020.5-2023.5 FI Scholarship awarded by AGAUR (Agency for Management of University and Research Grants) 2019.9-2020.5 CSC Scholarship awarded by Chinese Scholarship Council

XIXIAN LIAO · RÉSUMÉ MAY 31, 2022

LANGUAGES Mandarin Chinese (native), English (IELTS C1), Spanish (DELE C1) SKILLS Python, Java, R, HTML, Visual Basic Courses **Machine Learning** Standford, online Coursera September 20, 2020 [Certificate] The FIDU (Initial Training in University Teaching) Programme in Translation and Online **Language Sciences** Universitat Pompeu Fabra September 21th 2020 - June 30th 2021 • [Certificate] From Draft to Submission: Publishing an Article or Book Chapter in English Online Universitat Pompeu Fabra February 2021 • [Certificate] **Statistics for Language studies** Online Universitat Pompeu Fabra May 2021 • [Certificate] Participation in Conferences _____ The 2021 Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP) November 7-11, 2021 Sinn und Bedeutung 26 September 8-10, 2021 **GeCKo symposium: Integrating Generic and Contextual Knowledge** May 18th, 2020 The 28th edition of the Conference of the Student Organisation of Linguistics in Europe January 29-31, 2020 (ConSOLE 28) **Deep Learning Barcelona Symposium 2019** December 19-20, 2019 **Membership in Scientific Association**

Languages & Skills_

Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL)

2021 - present